<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lamentable discourse, vpon the paricide and bloudy assasination: committed on the person of Henry the fourth (of famous memorie) King of France and Navarre. Translated out of the French copy, printed at Rouen by Peter Courant, and the copie of Paris, printed by Francis Huey, with permission</title>
            <title>Discours lamentable sur l'attentat commis en la personne de très-heureuse mémoire Henri IIII. English</title>
            <author>Pelletier, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847425</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847425</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12458</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09252)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12458)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 728:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lamentable discourse, vpon the paricide and bloudy assasination: committed on the person of Henry the fourth (of famous memorie) King of France and Navarre. Translated out of the French copy, printed at Rouen by Peter Courant, and the copie of Paris, printed by Francis Huey, with permission</title>
                  <title>Discours lamentable sur l'attentat commis en la personne de très-heureuse mémoire Henri IIII. English</title>
                  <author>Pelletier, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Pelletier, Pierre, fl. 1610, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Windet] for Edward Blunt and William Barret,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: "Pelletier". Often attributed to Pierre Pelletier, but "plus vraisemblant l'œuvre de Thomas Pelletier"--Bibliothèque nationale cat.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Discours lamentable sur l'attentat commis en la personne de très-heureuse mémoire Henri IIII.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Title page in facsimile from British Library copy.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610 --  Assassination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12458:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:12458:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> LAMENTABLE DISCOVRSE, VPON The paricide and bloudy aſſaſinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: committed on the Perſon of HENRY the fourth (of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie) King of FRANCE and NAVARRE.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the French Copy, Printed at Rouen <hi>by Peter Courant, and the Copie of Paris, Printed</hi> by FRANCIS HVBY, with permiſsion.</p>
            <figure>
               <q xml:lang="lat">PRO LEGE<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> REGE, ET GREGE</q>
               <q>LOVE KEPYTH THE LAWE, OBEYETH THE KYNGE AND IS GOOD TO THE COMMUN WELTHE ·❀·</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Blunt</hi> and <hi>William Barr<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12458:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:12458:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
            <head>A LAMENTABLE DISCOVRSE VPON THE PARRICIDE AND BLOVDIE aſſaſination committed on the perſon of H<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> the fourth of famous memory, <hi>King of France and of Nauarre.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not the property of greateſt ſorrowes, to ſpeak much, for teares &amp; heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking ſighes are fitteſt demonſtrations to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the greateſt paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which maketh mee expreſſe in fewe Words, the great griefe, and publique ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row France at this time ſuffereth: nowe then, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> poſſerity euer lament, that laſt Friday, the foureteenth daye of May: the next day after the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, and coronation of the Queene out great <hi>Henry</hi> (or moſt famous memory) King of France and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12458:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->beeing at Paris about three of the clocke in the afternoone, intended to goe to his Arcenall: tooke his Caroch, and as a Prince which liued without feare or ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his people, paſſed through the City, accompanied with fewe of his Nobilitie; without taking for his better aſſurance, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Archers, or any of his vſuall Gard.</p>
            <p>But miſchiefe, or rather our ſinnes procured, that an accurſed and execrable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſigne named <hi>Francis Rauaill<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt,</hi> borne in Angouleſme, approached his perſon, not farre from S. Innocents; where ſeeing his Maieſties Caroche ſtayed by a Cart, which met and ſtopped their paſſage; taking op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, aſſaulted with moſt helliſh fury this good King, with a long knife, made of purpoſe; with which hee gaue him two wounds in the left ſide: the firſt was giuen nigh the ſhoulder, which entered not farre; but onely raſed the skinne: the ſecond was mortall, the blowe entering betwixt the fift and ſixt rib, cut aſunder the veine lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the heart; and the wound was ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12458:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->deepe, that it reached into the <hi>Caua Vena,</hi> which was pierced with the point of the knife. The Prince finding himſelfe woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to death, loſt vpon the inſtant his ſpeech, by reaſon of the aboundance of bloud, which iſſued outo his mouth, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they turned the caroch to the Louu're, where hee was no ſooner arriued, but hee rendred his ſoule into the hands of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God; teſtifying with his eyes and hands lifted vp to heauen, that hee died a true Chriſtian and good Catholique: My Lord the Archbiſhop of Ambrun, doing the laſt ſeruice of a Church-man, exhorted him in this laſt action.</p>
            <p>Is it not now a wonder to the Chriſtian world, to ſee France a ſecond Affrike, bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch deteſtable mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſters? What ſhame doth this age breede to that of our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? What diſaſtre that a king of France ſhould not eſcape the rage &amp; fury of a cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throat villaine his owne ſubiect? Wicked villaine, thou haſt bereaued vs of this great Prince, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with teares, &amp; whoſe loſſe we ſhall euer feele. Thou thoughteſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12458:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->in thy damnable deſsigne to ſwallow vs vp in a gulfe of miſery and deſolation. but God in his goodneſſe hath relieued vs, and otherwiſe diſpoſed the hearts and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the French, then thou in thy frenzie diddeſt imagine, or the helliſh counſell of Sathan ſuggeſt. The darke priſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou art iuſtly encloſed, where new tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are inuented and prepared to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe thy offence, will not let thee ſee, how that for all thy wicked act, all things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant in the ſame tranquility they were before. It is to Gods grace alone we owe the thanks, yet denie not due praiſe to thoſe inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts he hath vouchſafed to vſe: for the Lords Officers of the Crowne, this famous Court of Parliament, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats of Paris, haue al with one heart &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſent, ſuccored &amp; aſſured the eſtate; ſo that there is not any ſhew of commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſedition amongſt this great people: Reſolution and modeſtie, which maketh the Pariſians much to be commended, and ſerueth as an example to all the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12458:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->of the Realme.</p>
            <p>Thou (I ſay) canſt not ſee how in the ſame houre of thy horrible attempt, all the Nobility ran to the Louu're offering, and proteſting their fidelity; thou ſeeſt not though the father be taken away, the ſonne is left vs, to ſucceede in gouernment, yong though he be, yet ſhall he be ſtrengthened with the ſage aduiſe of great Princes, &amp; the Queene his mother, who a midſt her great griefes will remember the common good; and hath vouchſafed for our comfort to accept the Regencie, and gouernment of the kingdome. In the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Princes Peeres, the Conſtable, the Chancelour, the Cardinals, the Marſhals of France, &amp; other the great officers of the State, all aſſembled in the great Chamber of the Pallace, with authority of the Court of Parliament, his lawfull ſucceſſour ſitting in his throne, was ſolemnly acknowledged, and proclaimed king of France the fifteenth of May.</p>
            <p>In ſumme, this young Prince is ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily brought vp, in the loue, and feare of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12458:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->God with all other vertues; which ſerue to the ornament of a great king, that treading in the footeſteps of the late king his father hee will cheriſh Religion, loue Iuſtice, be generous, meeke, affable, gracious, and ſhine in a full luſtre as a faire ſunne ouer all France. All things ſhall flouriſh vnder his raigne, his people ſhall bleſſe him, &amp;c with fixed eyes to heauen, ſhall pray God for his happy preſeruation.</p>
            <p>Thus now we ſee, this Prince happily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, ſo well maintained, with force of armes, aduiſe of Councell, and loue of his ſubiects: that it ſhall be in vaine, for any to dare to ſtir without receiuing condigne chaſtiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: ſince then the entry to his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is ſo bleſſed, and ſeconded with the fauours of heauen, let vs not prouoke the anger of God, by out euill demeanors; let vs ſo behaue our ſelues, that amongſt all the French, onely this aſsaſine be dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and held in abhomination amongſt ſtrangers, let vs remenber that as there is nothing that raiſeth tempeſts at Sea, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12458:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->contrary winds, ſo nothing that troubleth a ſtate but diſunion if our owne iudgment and capacitie canot inſtruct vs, yet let the ſchoole of reaſon reach vs, let vs conſider that in a humane body, there is an head, and vnder that head many noble parts, that the member that is deſtined to one ſeruice, dareth not exerciſe another office, the legs will not be the armes nor the lun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the hart; likewiſe in a well ordered e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, one is acknowledged for head, &amp; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/> giueth life to all the other members, which worke nor mooue but vnder his authority, ſo that euery one acquitting himſelfe of his dutie. by a good vnion and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence, kingdomes are conſerued &amp; of ſmall ones become great: whereas contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywiſe by diſunion and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ars, great ones haue beene ruinated, and come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>Remember you French men: that it is aboue 1200. yeres, ſince <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he kingdome of France, hath bin <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euerenced for one of the greateſt Monarchies in the world, tak heed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12458:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->that poſterity do not reproach vs, that the mine of it happened in our age<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And that by our rage we haue demoliſhed, that which our aunceſtors haue raiſed by their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and valours: and if the publicke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt money on not let euery one at leaſt be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> of his ow<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> particular we are all e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>barked in one veſſell, if it pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, it will be <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ell if any of vs eſcape: we are all in one <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, if that fall weſhall al be ouerwhelmed in the <gap reason="illegible" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>er Let vs not forget, that we are yet wet with our laſt ſhip wracke, that it is not many yeeres, ſince we we<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e freed from ciuill wars<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the deſolation wherof neuer comes alone, but is alwaies attended with plague, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and all othe ſort of calamitie, as the loſſe of our goods, and eſtates, the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment and ranſoming of our bodies, the ſacke and ſpoile of our Cities, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhing of our wiues &amp; daughters, &amp; the bloody death of our children<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Let vs know that experience is the miſtreſſe of fooles, let vs not waite to repent of the miſchiefe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12458:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->we haue felt the ſmart by our folly: Wee are now in peace, let vs continue preſerued, and ſeeke to maintaine it by the helpe of God. Let vs not bee like ſorcerers, and Magitians, which cauſe raine, and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by their charmes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the courſe of Nature miſchiefes, and m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeries come but too ſoone, let vs not prouoke them, or goe to meete them.</p>
            <p>You great ones which haue the charge and gouernment of the kingdome, in the name of God, haue no other obiect before your eyes, but the good and ſeruice of your King, aboue all flie diſunion, which like a wicked Counſailour ſeeking to ruine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ouerthrowes it ſelfe, aſſure your ſelues, the greatnes of the eſtate, is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your owne, her tranquility and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhement, is the baſe and foundation of your owne families. Study not who ſhall ouerthrow his companion, but who ſhall beſt &amp; moſt faithfull ſerue his Country; it is onely the property of weake and ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low men, to fleſh themſelues with enuie,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12458:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->rancour, and diſsimulation; carie you all your hearts in your faces. loue one an<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her that you may the better ſerue one Maſter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It ſhall be your proſperity, and doubt not but that in a ſtate there are more good the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wicked, and that there was neuer any mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous or factious, but in the end was cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the authority of his Soueraigne.</p>
            <p>You haue at this day a king redoubta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ouer whoſe perſon the eye of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth ſo wateh, that though he be yet young, hee ſhall not be the leſſe obeyed or feared throughout all his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: the Edicts of the late king his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhall be obſerued as his owne: you ſhall haue him a common father ouer his people.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid that <hi>Alexander,</hi> made no diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction betwixt Greeke and Barbarian, but only by their v<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtues, not reſting vpon the difference of their habite. So our king ſhal iudge who are good and bad French men, onely by the marke of their obdience, and fidelity: euery one ſhall haue part of his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12458:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->grace and fauour, as he ſhall make himſelfe worthy by his ſeruice.</p>
            <p>In ſuch ſort, that all thinges beeing ſo firmely eſtabliſhed within the Realme, we ſhall not haue cauſe to feare any danger from without the king is in peace with his neighbours, and we aſſure our ſelues there is none of them, but is ſo good and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that he doth deplore this ſiniſter acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, happened to the late king, &amp; though he had, before the death of this Prince, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes &amp; means to endammage France, he doth now turne his hate into loue, moued onely by commiſeration of this diſaſter: And if we may now hope for this tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart from Princes, which be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, what ought we to expect from thoſe who are naturally borne French? God for his mercy inſpire France with ſo much of his grace, that not wanting counſell, true and lawfull commaund, wee may render that obedience and ſubmiſsion, which good and loyall ſubiects, owe vnto their Soueraigne. <hi>Pelletier.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
